Guide to the Padraic Colum Letters and Manuscripts
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Padraic Colum Letters and Manuscripts,
1918-1966
Colum, Padraic, 1881-1972.
0.5 linear ft (28 items in 1 box).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078627
Biographical Note
Irish poet and playwright.
Scope and Content
Letters of Padraic Colum to various persons. Also, several of Colum's manuscripts, notably three volumes containing drafts of his play, "Balloon."
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 3 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence, 1916-1969
Series II: Works, 1907-1973
Series III: Personal Papers and Photographs, 1898-1943
Subjects
English literature--Irish authors.; English literature--20th century.; Manuscripts.; Scripts.; Poets, Irish.; Dramatists.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1963 M-63 Upjohn, Everard M. Gift
Gift of Everard M. Upjohn, 1963; Andrew B. Myers, 1976, 1981, & 1988; The Gotham Book Mart in honor of the 95th birthday of Frances Steloff.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence, 1916-1969
  The series contains letters from Padraic Colum. It is arranged chronologically, with undated letters at the end.
  - Colum, Padraic To: Harvey Norris, New York, 12 December 1916, (1p. a.n.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Padraic, Colum To: Grace Walcott Hazard Conkling, New York, 26 February 1918., (1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Katherine Lord., [New York], 7 November 1920., (1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Sharon O. Brown, Dublin, 22 September 1925, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: William Stanley Beaumont Braithwaite, on board the R.M.S. Aquitania, [c. 1930], (2p. a.l.s. with t.l. copy) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Sr. Mary James, New York, [c. 1930], (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Pirie [MacDonald], Paris, [ca. December 1934], (1p. a.n.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Frank, Peterboro, NH, 24 September 1930, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Pirie MacDonald, paris, 20 August 1932, (2p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Pirie MacDonald, [Nice], July 1933, (1p. a.p.c.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Mrs. M.L.T. Davis, Jr. South Norwalk, Connecticut, 17 October 1938, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To Mrs. M.L.T. Davis, [Jr.], Paris; New York, 17 October 1938; 8 November 1938, (1p. t.l.s., 2p. a.l.s with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Emilie MacDonald (Mrs. Pirie), New York, 10 May 1942, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Emilie MacDonald (Mrs. Pirie), Wood's Hole, Mass., 27 June 1942, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: J. Morris Jones, Wood's Hole, Mass., 28 July 1944, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To Peter Russell, New York, 23 April 1951, (2p. t.l.s. with 2 clippings) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: George Heavey, New York, 27 December 1955, (2p. t.l.s. with 3 draft replies of 6 January 1956) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Warren Bower, Wood's Hole, Mass., 23 August 1958, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Marshall Bean, 3 October 1966, (1p. a.l.s. and photograph of painting of Colum, n.p. [ca. 1966] signed twice and inscribed to Marshall Bean) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Mrs. Mark Smith, New York, 16 January 1969, (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Carmer, Carl] To: Padraic Colum, n.p., n.d., (1p. t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Colum, Padraic To: George Reavey, New York, n.d., (1p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Mrs. Hobart B. Upjohn, New Canaan, Conn., n.d., (2p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colum, Padraic To: Diethelm, Wood's Hole, Mass., n.d., (1p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Works, 1907-1973
  The series contains original drafts of Colum's works along with a few published articles. The series is divided into Plays, Novels, Poetry, Reviews and Works on Colum.
  - Subseries II.1: Plays
    - Padraic, Colum Three ms. notebooks containing the draft of his play: Balloon, [ca.1929] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Colum, Padraic The Hen Wife's Son from The Flying Swans, [New York], [1947-1948], (92 p. a.ms., ) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries II.2: Poetry
    The subseries contains original manuscripts of poems by Colum.
    - An old woman of the roads a.ms.s., published in Wild Earth, 1907; These upright flowers: until the chestnuts bloom... a.ms.s., 2p.; The vision single and sure a.ms.s., 1 p.; Wild ass t.ms.s. 1 p., published in Dramatic Legends and Other Poems 1922, New York, 1907-1922 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subseries II.3: Criticism by Colum
    - The Dublin Magazine with a review of two poets by Padraic Colum, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Subseries II.4: Works on Colum
    - The Journal of Irish Literature: A Padraic Colum Number, Vol. II, No. 1, Jan., 1973, (An entire edition dedicated to the life of the poet, playwright: Padraic Colum ) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series III: Personal Papers and Photographs, 1898-1943
  The series includes photographs of Colum, a contract for an automobile sale, and a list of portraits (including Colum) at the New York Historical Society.
  - Photographs; personal contracts, n.d., (Photograph of bust of Colum by Edmund Quinn in the Dublin Municipal Gallery, signed. Portrait as a young man, signed, c. 1898. List of 500 Portraits of Men by Pirie MacDonald at the New York Historical Society, (including Colum), 1943 ) (Box 1, Folder 8)